<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moderator expecting sudden peace, or certaine ruine. Directed by reason, arising out of the consideration of what hath already happened, our present condition, and the most likely consequents of these.</title>
            <author>Povey, Thomas, fl. 1633-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E89_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859910</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90886)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E89[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moderator expecting sudden peace, or certaine ruine. Directed by reason, arising out of the consideration of what hath already happened, our present condition, and the most likely consequents of these.</title>
                  <author>Povey, Thomas, fl. 1633-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16, 15-28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno Domini, 1642. [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Povey. cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "by auditor Povie [illegible]; "feb: 16th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112012:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MODERATOR EXPECTING SVDDEN PEACE, OR CERTAINE RUINE.</p>
            <p>Directed by Reaſon, Ariſing out of the Conſideration of what hath already happened, Our preſent Condition, and the moſt likely Conſequents of Theſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Tales Caſus Caſſandra canebat.</l>
               <l>— Quem tum vates Caſſandra moveret?<note place="margin">Virgil. Aeneid. Lib. 3.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Cedamus Phoebo, &amp; moniti meliora ſequamur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112012:2"/>
            <head>THE MODERATOR EXPECTING Sudden PEACE, OR Certaine RVINE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Amongſt the many complaints poſterity may juſtly take up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, it ſhall never be ſaid, that we did all wilfully blind the eyes of our reaſon, and would not ſee the Euills, which with an unveiled face ſhewed themſelves, in their full horror, before they came upon us. For my part, if I muſt periſh, my fate and want of prevention not of foreſight ſhall betray me to it; whilſt the reſults of our deſignes, and the miſeries that muſt neceſſarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us, offer themſelves ſo eaſily to our apprehenſion, before we feele them. But it is not our meere contemplative providence, but a diſcreet exerciſe of it, that can be able to reſcue us from the ruine that attends us. And though it is not the pious care of a few ſingle men, that can ſave even themſelves, much leſſe the periſhing ſtate, whoſe decayed Fabrick is on every ſide undermined, and ready to fall in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet ſurely it is every mans duty to lend his beſt aſſiſtance to the common ſafety, becauſe if we periſh it muſt be by our owne hands. And ſince it is at out owne election what ſhall become of us? Let us call reaſon to adviſe with, let us throughly looke into our condition: And theſe ſad and ſerious conſiderations, may perhaps reclaime many of us from the eager purſuit of things, which we have too violently fancied to our ſelves, out of conveniency, neceſſity, or ſome other politique reaches, to advantage our ſelves or the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique. We are now arrived almoſt to the extremity of ill; and yet ſome beleeve that there is a way to grow better, by growing worſe. I pray Heaven this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox may not undoe us.</p>
            <p>But before we ſet one foot forward, and march on to the conſiderations which are before us, let us make a ſtand, and take a review of the actions and ſucceſſe, which we have already had, in the high conteſtations between Prince and People.</p>
            <p>VVarres, like diſeaſes, are a long while working upon the humors, before
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112012:2"/>they diſcover themſelves: And there are indeed many things of conſe quence, that did ſecretly fore run and uſher in this Warre, which I ſhall at moſt but touch upon. The curious ſearching into theſe things may perhaps inflame, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not qualifie our diſtempers. Our proper intereſt now is to get out of theſe miſeries, to which we ſeem to have been unhappily betrayed, by endeavouring without ſucceſſe, (ſaith one,) or providence, (ſaith another,) or enough of both (ſaith a third, for thus boldly men diſcourſe now) a high and Imperious refo mation; which by the cunning uſe that Delinquents, the Prelacy, and the Agents for Prerogative have made of it, hath in ſtead of removing, created new oppoſites: and thoſe have ſo faſted themſelves, that they cannot be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne without more then endangering the very foundations of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. And we are making ſo much haſte to the Ruine, which that grand Engineer the Jeſuite hath this many yeeres been deſigning for us, that we have two Armies fighting againſt themſelves, for the common good: and they are now growne both ſo conſiderable, that it is almoſt impoſſible that any good can be effected by them, untill very many thouſands more ſhall fall by the Sword; and, how we ſhall call any thing good, that ſhall be bought at ſo bloody a price. I know not. Let us but trace the foot-ſteps of our miſ-fortunes, and we ſhall ſee by what degrees we are grown into theſe extremities. And how we have (is it were by inches) engaged our ſelves into new and deſperate miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes. How one extreame hath begot another: And whilſt we have had one deſigne to overcome a prevailing evill, we have by that raiſed up a worſe. I have heard that Poiſon hath ſometimes been wrought out by a contrary poyſon; but the wary Phiſitian holds the cure but deſperate, and ſcarce can tell, which is moſt deſtructive the Medicine or the Diſeaſe: For where the conteſtation is ſo violent, it ſeldome happens that it doth not deſtroy the Patient. To come cloſer: It ſeemes our peace was ſo corrupt, that it was held requiſite it muſt be lanced with the Sword. I pray Heaven our Chirurgions cut not ſo farre, that inſtead of letting out Putrifaction; they let not out our very Vitals, by too deep, too wide a wound. But I ſhal make haſte to my promiſe, which is to make it evident, how deſtructive this kind of Deciſion hath been and muſt be to us; which will appeare from the firſt Overtures of it, and in every thing that hath happened ſince.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Militia,</hi> the <hi>Navy,</hi> and the <hi>Ports</hi> (which were the common ſtrength of the Kingdome) were firſt put into new confiding hands (whether out of prevention or preparation) I looked upon this action, as like to that Cloud, which firſt ſhewed it ſelfe to the <hi>Prophets ſanvant,</hi> to be as big as a mans hand; and I feared that I ſhould afterward ſee it darken all our <hi>Heavens,</hi> all our happineſſe: and at laſt fall into fatall and bloody ſhowers. <hi>Iealouſie</hi> of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure is the <hi>Fore-runner</hi> and <hi>Inflamer</hi> of all <hi>Miſchiefe;</hi> when this diſcovered it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112012:3"/>ſelfe ſo plainly in the <hi>King;</hi> and had ſo divided not onely the Head from the Members, but the Members amongſt themſelves: he that did not then feare conſequences of a high and dangerous nature, was too ſecure; and ſurely never conſidered, that a <hi>Parliament</hi> is the <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>State;</hi> and when that was poyſoned with <hi>jealouſie:</hi> it ſubtilly mingled it ſelfe with every County as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving it from the <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> Here the people might take the firſt notice of the conteſtation; And from that time they encountered each other with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective Declarations (worſe then Gun-ſhot) which heightned the quarrell, and invited the amuzed people to lay aſide their peace; and ſhew themſelves, on which ſide they would rather chooſe to hazard their fortunes. Here began the firſt eager Diviſion: for by this means, the diſcountenanced <hi>Gentry</hi> (who were removed from their <hi>Commands,</hi> and ſo, from the uſuall reſpect they had in their Country) faſtned themſelves in opinions oppoſite to the Parliamentary proceedings: And the common people, diſputing over earneſtly of theſe things) did at laſt, according to the reaſon they were able to ſee, diſcourſe themſelves into a reſolute conceit of things, which as their paſſions and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours led them) they have all this while proſecuted.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Subjects</hi> being now ſtirred, and divided: The great <hi>Gameſters</hi> of the State goe higher; The more active of the <hi>Parliament</hi> are accuſed by the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Treaſon:</hi> The <hi>Kings Adviſers,</hi> to whoſe Councels He ſeemed moſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here are impeached by the <hi>Parliament</hi> for <hi>Traitors.</hi> And now they hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves concerned to ſtand, or fall, with thoſe that both ſides aymed at. So that it is time that they be further aſunder: for diſtance affords many advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages to worke a <hi>Deſigne</hi> higher, or elſe may be a meanes to compoſe thoſe differences, which are ſtill renewing, whilſt the <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> are together. The <hi>King</hi> therefore removes <hi>Northward,</hi> to finde out that ſafety, which (he ſaith) is denyed him here: and to gaine a party to ballance thoſe, whom already he accounts his Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus the Scene</hi> begins to alter; and inſtead of reforming (the proper worke of <hi>Parliament:</hi>) we ſhall ſee it buſied and almoſt puzled in ſaving (for ſo they call it) a diſtreſſed <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> And from henceforth, we muſt looke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a Councell of <hi>War,</hi> and muſt not expect to finde it punctuall in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of any fixed <hi>Law:</hi> but that Common Law, called <hi>Salus populi,</hi> muſt be produced as a generall warrant for all their undertakings: And that <hi>Statute Law</hi> enacted even by Nature it ſelfe, called <hi>Lex neceſſitatis;</hi> muſt be made to juſtifie all manner of <hi>ſeverity</hi> and <hi>violence.</hi> And this muſt be all the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the complaining Subject ſhall be able to obtaine.</p>
            <p>The moſt eminent diſcovery of this <hi>Warre;</hi> which openly offered it ſelfe to the conſideration of the People, was that great contention about the Town of <hi>Hull.</hi> And although it coſt not much blood; yet was it made an occaſion to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112012:3"/>ingage the buſineſſe very far. The <hi>Warre</hi> was ſooner ſeen to the people, then the <hi>Reaſons</hi> of it: and though they could not define what the quarrell was; yet they begin to finde that they muſt end it, and ſeele the effects of it. And, to ſtartle them the more, their doubts are nouriſhed and increaſed by the well penned papers from the North: and in a few monthes, are perſwaded to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe that, which the Actions, and the ſenſe of many yeeres before, had almoſt confirmed in them. Thus, the <hi>King</hi> perceives, that to defend the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty and liberty of his Subjects, (though but with the ſhadow of them) with promiſes and proteſtations, catches the affections of his <hi>credulous People;</hi> and almoſt recovers and fixes them in their obedience. How much then, will they be his, when theſe promiſed bleſſings ſhall be theirs in earneſt?</p>
            <p>And what advantage have we had by any thing hath yet been acted by the ſword? what preſent reparation or what likly hopes, hath the abuſed ſubject for the expence of ſo many millions? for the loſſe of ſo much bloud? and for dangerous hazard of their peace? that jewell which indeed we know not how to value, untill it be loſt? Some of the Malignants bloud hath been had, though bought with as much of the adverſe party. Our Townes have been yielded and recovered on both ſides; whole Countries have been plundred; thouſands have been undon; Skirmiſhes we have had in many places. A ſet Battaile (the wiſh of our Sonnes of <hi>Mars</hi>) hath been fought with almoſt equall loſſe aud ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; as if Heaven had told us wee are both in fault; both worthy of an overthrow, but neither of us of victory: the beſt part of a yeere hath beene made up happy whileſt every day ſaw new <hi>Tragedies.</hi> And after all this, how much nearer, nay how much farther of, are we from the Peace, or from the Endes we ſeemed to aime at? The quarrell by all this, is but inflamed; jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies grow higher; Malice growes ſtronger; Poverty comes upon us like an armed man: Humanity is almoſt turned to cruelty, and Nature and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, are not able to reſtraine our inconſiderate fury. The Sword muſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after become chiefe Juſtice; and will diſpence with and controll all Law. From hence-forth Robbery ſhall change its name, and be called no more a crime then borrowing: the killing of our Country men muſt be called valour, and a ſervice to the State: the oppoſing our ſelves againſt the chiefe Fort and ſtrength of the ſubject, the great councell of Parliament, muſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Allegiance and duty: diſobedience to the commands of our Prince, muſt be called Loyalty: and in briefe, (ſuch is the tyranny of Warre) we muſt ſee an inverſion of all order, Conſuſion in all our ſervices to Heaven and Earth; and a <hi>Chaos,</hi> in ſtead of that admirable compoſure which many yeares of peace had ere now fixed this ſtate in; if thoſe that have of late times beene over us, had done their partes: How like to theſe calamities the miſeries we have felt already, are, the ſad experience of too many may witneſſe; who have drinke
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112012:4"/>deep of this bitter Cup: But the dregs are as yet behind; in which every ſurviver muſt have a ſhare, if Heaven will have us to pledge its vengeance farther.</p>
            <p>Although ſuch times as theſe will ſearce give us leave to call any thing our own; yet I hope they will let us enjoy the uſe of our reaſon ſtill, which ſhall alwayes lead my Faith, and expectation in ſuch open affaires as theſe. And when that ſhall tell me how requiſite the proſecution of this War is, and how it may advantage the ſtate, I ſhall be convinced; but untill then. I ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in this opinion (hoping that it will not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out to to be againſt the ſence of the Parliament: <hi>That a peace warily conclud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by an Accomodation muſt be the happieſt iſſue that can be given to theſe Differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ere I lettled my ſelfe in this opinion, I enquired out (as far as poſſible I could) all the conveniences and inconveniences, that W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce may beget, and as wel as my reaſon would give me leave, have weighed, which are likely to be the heavieſt. And I hope I ſhall be excuſed by every one, that ſhall deſcend into theſe following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what probably this War aimes at, in this conjecture, it will befit us to be very modeſt, and rather to thinke, then to ſpeake out: we ſhall not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine what all yance (I meane in the birth of it) there is betwixt this, and that with the <hi>Scots.</hi> Now whether the prerogative commenced it, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect it ſelfe againſt an invading power, which ſeemed to threaten it, (as ſome would have it) or to perfect the deſigne of many yeares before, to be abſolute maſter of the people, (as others conceive) or whether the Parliament begun it to ſecure themſelves, and fetch in Delinquents, (as we are bid believe) or to confirm that by the ſword, which no other aſſurance could ever make good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; and to bring the government ſome-what neere to an Ariſtocracie (as ſome have ſuggeſted;) Or whether indeed this reaſon of the War be a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celany of all theſe. But how juſtifiable, how neceſſary, and on which ſide this War was defenſive or offenſive, I ſhall not undertake to debate or determine. Theſe are dangerous myſteries, not to be pried into. It wil be enough for us to enquire how far it tends to the generall good; by what hath already happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and what muſt happen in the proſecution of it.</p>
            <p>We muſt believe (where ere this War began) that it was levied by well weighed pollicy, and upon conſiderate grounds; and we muſt not conceite but the deſigne was only to ſecure the Kingdome, and reſcue it, from ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that are in the boſome of it, which have malignantly thwarted the long-looked for bleſſings of this Parliament. And it is confeſſed (though not agreed on) by both Armies, that our Religion, Lawes, Liberties, and whatſoever is or ſhould be deare unto us, lies at the ſtake; and that they weare their Swords only to defend theſe: and that theſe cannot be ſafe, unleſſe one of them prove victorious.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112012:4"/>
            <p>Thus our cauſe is much like a riddle; It were ſurely better for us, to have it underſtood by the deliberation and wiſdome of a parley, then by ſuch meanes as <hi>Alexander</hi> uſed to unty the <hi>Gordian</hi> knot, the violence of the ſword. If Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be the principall reaſon; how few hopes have we to ſee it rectified by War which is the nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of barbariſme. The Souldier the inſtrument of this kind of reformation (after he ſhall be a little more ve ſed in his rude profeſſion we ſhall ſcarce ever finde devoted to any thing of Religion beſides the pretence and noyſe of it, in their talke, only to ſet a gloſſe upon their quarrell: from them we muſt looke for little elſe, but prophanation and ſacriledge. And ſuppoſe theſe men of War prove more civill and pious then all other Souldiers before them what religion ſhall we expect to be exerciſed during this War, which wil be a continuing Holy-day to all licentiouſneſſe? when as in this neceſſitated intermiſſion of ſtrict government how many new fancied religions boldly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves? how little reverence, and how much prophanation have we ſeen? Religion is a child of peace, and if an aged peace have the foſtering of it, it will be hard to keepe it cleare from innovations, and ſuperſtition, (the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of the idle Clergy) and that ſtate that cannot, or will not remove theſe miſchiefes without the ſword, endangers the very body of it, whilſt it would only lop off the extravagancies.</p>
            <p>Such effects as theſe, we can only looke for, when a laſting War ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to compoſe a divided Church: it may (ſome have thought) happen otherwiſe, if the deſigne be ſo adviſedly laid and ſo rigorouſly proſecuted that the execution of it ſhal be ſuddaine.</p>
            <p>But, it will be told me, when the Parliaments Army hath gotten the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and all oppoſitions, ſhall be removed, ſo that they may without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reach their ends, ſuch a Reformation will be effected, as ſhall recompence the diſturbance in the gaining of it. Any man that conſults with his unbiaſſed reaſon, cannot well promiſe this to himſelfe: for we ſhall finde ſuch a victory and ſuch a reformation very doubtfull. But we will ſuppoſe them conquerors. It hath been the opinion of ſome; that ſucceſſe may ſomewhat heighten their religious deſignes; and ſuggeſt ſuch things as eaſy, and convenient, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their very imagination durſt not reach at. Then they will have time to conſider all their oppoſites, even thoſe, who (before this reformation grew ſo violent) were accounted Puritans. Then it is likely, neither roote nor branch, of our old Church order ſhall be left nor any ſigne where it grew And though perhaps themſelves could be contented with a more even and moderate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; It may be ſeared that the loud people, delighting in change, and growen inſolent with their ſucceſſe will call for a mutation in every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and when they have found their ſtrength, will thinke nothing enough if they have not all that their wild and unlimitted <hi>Zeale</hi> approves of.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:112012:5"/>
            <p>And (if ſome miſtaken not) the intereſt of the Parliament will then be, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a more tigid government (to ſay no more) in the Church, then will now ſatisfy them and all modeſt Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>And on the contrary, our condition cannot well be ſuch as we could wiſh it, if the ſubjects of <hi>England</hi> make the King a Conquerour whether he will or no (nor is this impoſſible.) Doe we believe the prelacy and the other ambitious Clergy, will then be any whit leſſe inſolent then they have been? will they not rather adde to, then diminiſh their ceremonies? will they not pretend that preaching hath ſeduced the people, and begat hereſies? that the Pulpit was the late in cendarie to the great miſchiefes, and therefore take a pious occaſion to be Idle, and make the abuſed people believe, that the Common Prayer tends more to their ſalvation, then the frequency of preaching? will theſe men of the caſſocks be leſſe vitious in their lives? leſſe corrupt in their Doctrine? leſſe exacting in their Tythes and pretended dues, then heretofore? And, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, will it lye in the intereſt or the power of the King, (when he ſhall be buſied to ſettle the confuſed Common-Wealth for his beſt advantage,) to bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle his Clergy, which ever were, are, and wil be the moſt conſiderable ſticklers when any buſtle or mutation happens in a ſtate; we muſt then looke to finde theſe ſort of men ſtill like themſelves, ſo buſy as if their imployment were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to improve prerogatives, then ſalvation. Their predeceſſors (Hiſtory tells us) were almoſt alwaies oppoſers of their Prince. And, (ſome are of opinion) that they doe otherwiſe now not becauſe their Religion, but their intereſt is altered. And (it hath been alwaies unhappily obſerued) that, their conſcience followes their dependancy; and that they put their caſes, and ſtate their queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as much by the motions of the latter as the former.</p>
            <p>And if there were ever any reaſon to be jealous of the incroaching power of papiſts, it will be then: for if the King (for his preſervation, and through neceſſity, the reaſons now urged upon this occaſion) be driven to make uſe of them to doe his buſineſſe and by their help become victorious; the Common people may ſeare that they ſhall hereafter ſee as much popery mingled in their worſhip as in their Armies: and thoſe of better judgement, cannot but conceive, that when Papiſts have merited ſo much from the King that they will be more modeſt with him, then with God, from whom they dare challenge a requitall for their merits: and upon ſuch a turne as this, it will be to their great advantage that the people (to whom the reputed Puritans and Round-heads muſt by all meanes be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dioas,) will be leſſe troubled, if ſome of thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere ſtatutes againſt them, be repealed, or deſpenſed with, and ſome other things be done in their favour; for being Buſtier Subjects to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (the firſt time, it was ever thought they could be ſo) then many of his Proteſtant Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:112012:5"/>
            <p>Such conſequences as theſe we muſt look for on both ſides, if the partiall ſword, and not the indifferent Synod muſt be the Eccleſiaſticall reformer.</p>
            <p>The Religion which all moderate men (and I thinke moſt, and beſt) deſire, is that which both ſides promiſe; and yet that which wee cannot well expect from either ſide, ſhould it become abſolute. It is ſuch a one as may be found out betwixt them both; and (wee may hope) may make all men happy, if it be tempered with a reaſonable yeelding on both ſides. But if the deciſion muſt be by blood and victory, the prevailers are then bound, and perhaps, neceſſitated to gratifie their party with that kinde of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline which their humours call for; they muſt looke to faſten themſelves by that power, and thoſe principles, by which they gained it. When as it is like to be quite otherwiſe, if peace ſuſpend theſe differences; both ſides muſt then goe on in an even and well tempered courſe, that they may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiquely hold faſt that party, which their promiſes and faire proteſtations won to them. It will then be hoped, that the contention will be, which ſhall be moſt plauſible; and it will be better for the people to have their affections invited then forced.</p>
            <p>Thus we find that Religion will looke moſt comely, dreſſed in the white garments of peace, rather then the purple robes of warre. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion is many times but a ſervant to other deſignes, and goes before, onely to uſher in ſome great affaire of State, in the ſame order it ſhall be followed now; and we ſhall in the next place examine how the State ſhall be bettered by a maſtery of either ſide.</p>
            <p>Would we have the Lawes better exerciſed which our Predeceſſors left to us? how much out of countenance Law is, when the ſword domineers, we need not be informed by Hiſtory. And when this warre ſhall ſee an end, with how much difficulty ſhall wee be rendred capable of the uſuall courſe and benefit of it? And we know not who by that time, may become Patron and Maſter of our Law and Nation: or would we have new Lawes to ſerve our turnes now? or confirme thoſe wee have gained this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? If that the ſword ſhall draw up new Statutes; it is likely they would be but ſhort lived, or uſeleſſe: for no politique ties; no, not the moſt ſacred aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of an oath, could ever make Princes obſerve the execution of them.</p>
            <p>And it may be feared, that ſuch violent gaining upon the Crown, may be an occaſion hereafter, to wreſt from us all thoſe advantages which the Subject hath dearely bought this Parliament, under pretence that violence was the mother of them all.</p>
            <p>Our liberties are not like to be much enlarged or ſecured by it, martiall Law will ere long diſſeize us of our Poſſeſſions, our Eſtates and Lives; and what Judge ſhall be able to redreſſe us? and wee muſt run a hazard, what kind of free-men or ſlaves wee muſt be hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112012:6"/>
            <p>So that upon all this enquirie, it is hard to bee ſatisfied how our Religion, Lawes or Liberties ſhall be improoved by ſuch a warre as wee are ingaged in, unleſſe the more pious and well-meaning party will promiſe certaine and ſudden ſucceſſe, both of which will be neceſſary to make it any thing likely; but of theſe more in the cloſe of all.</p>
            <p>But when we have ſupoſed, that wee ſhall be bettered in all theſe when the warre is ended; let us with an intentive eye, looke upon the miſeries which muſt be our entertainment whileſt the war continues: That which wee have ſeene or heard already of it, is no more then a ſad Prologue to an enſuing Tragedie, which onely tells us what wee are to expect; but the following acts thew us thoſe bloody paſſages at large.</p>
            <p>As yet the Souldier hath not devoured the Husband-mans ſtore; but, without much trouble findes <hi>Bread</hi> for himſelfe, and <hi>Provender</hi> for his <hi>Horſe;</hi> but where will hee ſeeke it, when hee hath ſpoyled the <hi>ſpringing graſſe,</hi> and trampled downe, or eaten up the <hi>growing corne?</hi> The Husband-man will be affraid to venture his ſeed in the <hi>ground,</hi> not knowing who ſhall reape it; or, if hee would be ſo hardie, perhaps, he wants his <hi>Horſes</hi> to plough, or his <hi>Hindes</hi> to helpe him.</p>
            <p>And ſuch will be our griefe, that wee muſt not looke for ſuccour from our neighbour Counties: for every one of them is like to be the <hi>Seat</hi> of warre; and ſo many Armies muſt needs conſume Cattle and Sheep, and the Farmers ſtocke, and ſo beget a famine. A famine never comes without ſad companions; as the Plague, ſmall Pox, Flux, and many more ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of death.</p>
            <p>Thus Proviſion, the chiefe ſupport of this populous Kingdome, will be ſuddenly waſted; and thus, thoſe whom war ſpares, want or violent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes will devour; and ſo wee ſhall many wayes periſh without the ſword, yet by it.</p>
            <p>It is to no purpoſe to demonſtrate how the treaſure of this Land, heaped up by a long lived peace, will be ſuddenly powred out, and be ſeene no more: thus many times doth a carefull and aged father leave a hard gotten Patrimony to a ſcattering ſonne. And, how certaine the utter decay of trade (the livelihood of the State) will be; how Art that was comming into ſuch a perfection amongſt us, will be loſt, and, as it were, unlearnt; how lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the glory of our Nation, will be diſeſteemed and uſeleſſe, and changed into martiall Diſcipline: how poverty will ſo generally ſeize almoſt upon all; that the violence of it will every where create us new enemies (if the Souldier ſpares us) which will take away our goods by the authenticke Law of neceſſity, and ſnatch away the meate from our mouthes, making hunger their warrant.</p>
            <p>But I will purſue this common place no further; theſe are the generall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112012:6"/>conſequences of warre; wee will therefore reflect more cloſely upon our owne more peculiar miſchiefes.</p>
            <p>If wee muſt put off Peace untill another time, how deſperate are wee? For, thoſe that ingage us in a warre, are not able to tell us, when, where, how, and by whom it ſhall end, (this the late and ſad experience of other people may tell us.) The queſtion hereafter will be, not ſo much, where is the Right? But where is the Power? For the Right of Power muſt carry the buſineſſe. And then it will be beyond Probability that this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ever recover the purity of it's Religion, it's Lawes, it's Cuſtomes, it's Government, which have beene ſetling about five hundred yeeres; nor let our preſent Superiours be angry at the conjecture; for I cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe, who ſhall live to ſtrike the laſt blow. And it hath in all ages beene obſerved, that deſignes in warre change like Scenes in a Maſque, where we ſee new apparitions ere we are aware of them: And the events of one yeere, may, beyond all expectation, vary, or heighten the quarrell. And it is alwayes found, that ſucceſſe lifts men up above them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for a prevailing power ſeldome knowes any bounds or modeſtie, the Subject will want his old ſanctuary then, which our Predeceſſors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; for, Lawes are but the ligaments of Peace, and the Souldier will breake them like threads.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall be asked, why my bold imagination hath phanſied ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things as theſe? Wee will therefore ſee now gradually wee muſt come to ſuch a condition as this.</p>
            <p>And firſt, becauſe wee will not undertake to define the quarrell as it now ſtands, largely, nor ſawcily; we will conceive it thus: <q>
                  <hi>A working jealouſie, fixed in a divided Kingdome, both ſides chooſing rather to die then to truſt one another.</hi>
               </q> From this root muſt neceſſarily ſpring theſe incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences.</p>
            <p>The moſt uncharitable miſchiefe that a Common-wealth can be inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in, is, That wee muſt execute the deſignes of our enemies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves; that the King may receive his death from the hand of a Subject whileſt it is reached forth (if you will believe his Vowes) for his good and ſafety: that the father ſending his bullet at a venture, may kill his ſonne, or the ſonne his father; this is probable enough: but it is impoſſible, that brothers, kindred and friends ſhould not mingle in one anothers blood, (and, perhaps, purpoſely) wee ſee ſuch an eager diviſion in all Families. And it is ſo univerſall, that no Countie, ſcarce any Citie or Corporation is ſo unanimous, but they have diviſion enough to undoe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And it is evident enough, that this Rent will encreaſe untill wee ſhall be quite torne in pieces: For, when the fatall ſluce of bloud ſhall be drawne up higher; in all probabilitie, the veines of the remaining People
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112012:7"/>(ſwelling with revenge for their battered partie) are likely to be drained dry thorowout the Kingdome. If wee will leave our, differences to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute of the Sword, wee ſhall not want an Umpire; one that will come in to part us, or part ſtakes with us. Let this Mediatour chance to be of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion like ours, or of one quite oppoſite unto it; who ſhall pay the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers for their journey-work? Muſt money be raiſed for them? It muſt be digged for them; I beleeve little will be found above ground. Or muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſerve the turne? The Souldier ſeldome returnes with ſuch pay. Or moſt plunder ſatisfie them? This may ſtay their ſtomacks, although it be but the Reliques of our owne men of war; but will not be able to ſend them back againe. No; wee ſhall find that the intereſt of that State muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied either with our Ruine, or with mingling themſelves in our Eſtates and Government.</p>
            <p>Or ſuppoſe our neighbours will wink on purpoſe, and neglect their advantages, though it were meere ſottiſhneſſe to conceit ſo; upon whoſe purſe ſhall our enemies at home, our owne Armies live? Muſt the Countries maintaine them? It muſt bee then by the Farmer: but hee can neither ſow, nor reap, nor breed up, nor repaire his ſtock, in the heat of ſuch a war as ours. Elſe muſt the Clothier do it? whence ſhall he have his many neceſſaries, and how ſhall he vent his clothes? If theſe faile, the Countries cannot be long conſiderable, in enduring the burthen of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? Is it expected the Citie muſt doe all this? That little which they have got before hand, and make their ſtore, is ſo impaired, that it will ſcarce maintaine themſelves, unleſſe it be by a continued courſe of trading; which, as it is now languiſhing, ſo it will be, ere that time, quite dead and buried. The Citie is as it were the ſtomack, which digeſts the trading of the whole Kingdome; and afterwards returnes to everie ſeverall part of it, that nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment which ſupports it: if weakneſſe and obſtructions be found there, a conſumption ſoone ſteales upon the whole body. But ſuppoſe it were rich, and full enough to ſerve the turne; yet they will not let downe their milk to a violent hand: they muſt be ſtroked and humoured, elſe they will be ſtubborne. If they chance to be at diſcord, it will be hard to collect any conſiderable ſums; and if that diſcord be heightened (by the cunning pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of any) into a mutiny amongſt themſelves, they will be able to undoe one another, without the help of a draining Army. Thus wee may ſee, our neceſſities will encounter and overcome us, if wee muſt live and dye (and living thus is worſe than dying) in this lingring war. And after all theſe horrid executions of Fire, Sword, Famine, Peſtilence, and thoſe many other ſad conſequences of war; what face at the beſt will this Kingdome have? what a ruinous Nobilitie, what a decayed Gentrie, what a beggarly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie will it be peopled withall? And what age ſhall ever ſee thoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112012:7"/>Fewds eaten out, which theſe Civill Broyles will beget? For we ſhall find, that as Jealouſie was the mother of them, ſo Malice, Hatred, and Revenge, will be the iſſue. And when ſhall a State ſo diſtempered, look for a quiet, or a ſafe compoſure? For War, like a ſtrong diſeaſe, leaves many dregs and reliques behind it, which (though the maine Forces be disbanded, and it be no more an Army, a Fever) will puniſh the uncleanſed body with ſeverall fits and diſtempers.</p>
            <p>We ſhall find that men nurſed up in war grow ſick of peace, and are like Tinder, ready to be inflamed into ſedition, or high attempts, by everie ſpark which Ambition, or any other exorbitant deſire lets fall. And if it ſhall be held a neceſſarie policie to hold up a war in any other place, to ſpend their fiefie ſpirits, the State will be as good as beggered to be thus rid of them: And it may be feared, that the meaner ſort will forget the uſuall toyle of their former profeſſions, by the licentiouſneſſe in the war; and will never after be brought to endure order, or labour: and ſo will returne to corrupt the Common-wealth, with their lawleſſe manners.</p>
            <p>I could add many more Inſtances; but I think there needs no more to be urged, to ſhew us how miſerable wee muſt neceſſarily be. Yet I muſt not omit the Motive which diſtreſſed <hi>Ireland</hi> offers unto us: which now repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the verie Condition we muſt look for; if a ſudden Peace do not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily prevent it.</p>
            <p>If we could look upon it, as ready to be undermined, and falling into the Ocean, ſo that no footing would be left there for our Adverſaries, though we could not but pitie it, and our ſelves; yet then all our feares would bee drowned with it: but we muſt conſider it, as one of our maine Bulwarks, gained and fortified not without infinit expence of the treaſure and bloud of our Anceſtors: and that it is now ready to be poſſeſſed by a dangerous enemy, who from thence will for ever batter our Peace; and it is likely, may make ſuch breaches, as may let in hereafter (if we eſcape them now) as many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries as <hi>Ireland</hi> now groanes under. Nor are all theſe miſchiefes which I have ſummoned up, more certaine, than the ſucceſſe of either ſide is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; ſo that if we doe grant to ſatisfie ſuch as will on both ſides have it ſo, that nothing but the good of the State is intended; How ſhall we be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that that pious Partie (which truly hath the moſt right) ſhall have the ſucceſſe? and how ſoone they will be able to accompliſh it. For as I have proved, there will be nothing left us to be preſerved, if it hold out long. But upon conſideration, wee ſhall find that both the ſucceſſe, and the concluſion of it, are verie uncertaine. Wee know that God many times u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Sword, as well to avenge himſelfe upon his People, as his People upon one another: and, that neither ſide have deſerved ſo well, as to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe themſelves the maſterie; although they dare aver, their Cauſe is beſt.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112012:8"/>So that I ſhall rather direct my judgement by Reaſon, than Preſumptions; and ſhall therefore weigh theſe great Oppoſites, to find out which of them hitherto hath had the greater ſucceſſe, and which hath the moſt probable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages at this time.</p>
            <p>It is ſcarce a yeare ſince all affaires, of what nature ſoever, received their enlivening Influence from the King, through his Parliament: which like a Burning-glaſſe contracted the Sun beames into it ſelfe, and was able to give fire to almoſt any Deſigne it pleaſed to reflect on; but thoſe Rayes which did then diſplay themſelves beſide it, did ſpend themſelves in vaine. During this full Authoritie, they furniſhed themſelves with all meanes that might defend them from the Counter-plots of thoſe, who they had reaſon to beleeve, could not endure the ſtrict Reformation which was ſuddenly intended.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ere the People are aware, or know why, they ſee all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Ports and Ports of the Kingdome, the Navie, the <hi>Militia,</hi> and all the ſtrength of the State ſequeſtred from the immediate commands of the Prince. And becauſe there is little ſtrength in theſe things, unleſſe they bee manned and maintained with the affections and aſſiſtance of the People, ſuch courſes are taken as may encite the moſt.</p>
            <p>Therefore the firſt Remonſtrance (the unhappie Hiſtorie of the fore-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times) opened the eyes of the People (not uſed to ſee ſo far into ſuch Myſteries) and diſcovers enough to heighten a diſlike againſt ſuch, as muſt owne thoſe miſ-carriages, and a feare, that thoſe that heretofore contrived ſo many miſchiefes againſt the State, had not yet laid downe their Deſigne. And that this danger ſhould be more apparant, a concurrencie of plots and conſpiracies, both from abroad and home, is diſcovered by many ſeverall Intelligencers: ſo that ſcarce a day paſſes, in which the State ſeemes not to be delivered from ſome eminent treaſon.</p>
            <p>By this time their Feares are not leſſe than their Dangers, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution growes as great as their Feare: ſo that any reaſonable man could not beleeve that the Enemy that muſt doe all theſe fore-told miſchiefes, could lodge within us and riſe againſt us, without being ſuppreſſed in the verie infancie of the Deſigne. Yet wee have found, that notwithſtanding all theſe Politique Ground-works, and Preventions; the Prophecie of the Parliament is thus far come to paſſe, that wee are likely to be deſtroyed; but it wounds us deep, when wee conſider, who ſeeme to be partly the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioners of it.</p>
            <p>Hee therefore that ſhall conſider all circumſtances, cannot but think it almoſt impoſſible, that the King, lately ſo much out of favour with the People; ſo diveſted of all things that conduce to the making of a war (but Reſolution, and the diſcontents of a few others) ſhould bee able
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112012:8"/>to get together ſo conſiderable an Armie, and ſuch a party as dare ſhew themſelves in every quarter of the Kingdome: Nor had he done it, had not his agents gathered infinite advantages which were let fall to them by ſome whoſe intereſts ſhould have made them more wary. Some doe inferre out of this, That the King of <hi>England</hi> cannot complaine (though but in meere policy) but the paſſionate people will pity him, though they ſight againſt themſelves. If theſe finde themſelves oppreſſed with the effects of ſuch a warre, they are eaſily invited to change their party (as diſcontented men doe the ayre, and ſicke men their beds) though they be never the more eaſed by it; and had rather ſubmit themſelves to the naturall obedience of their Prince, then to the ſevere and unuſuall commands of any other power, though they are told, that they tend to their preſervation. Thus, by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe paſſed conſiderations wee finde that ſucceſſe doth often coozen out experiences; and will not alwayes follow humane deſignes, thongh they ſeeme to be grounded upon the moſt right and certaintie; and after all this ſtrugling and weakning of the Kingdome the oppoſion growes ſtronger, and the event ſtill more dangerous and doubtfull. Yet wee will ſee as farre as wee can at diſtance, on which ſide advantages leane moſt.</p>
            <p>The ground of ſuch a warre as this, is the affections of the People; and upon this, both Armies are built, and kept up: wee will therefore gueſſe which of them hath the ſureſt foundation. It hath been obſerved, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath made little difference, (or not the right) between the Gentry and Yeomanry, rather complying and winning upon the latter, then regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or applying themſelves at all to the former. And they may be thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed; they did not thinke it juſtice to looke upon any man according to his quality, but as hee was a Subject; I hope this was all the reaſon: but howſoever, it appeares not that they yet have, or are likely to gaine by this policie. The common people, could they be fixed, were onely worth the courting at ſuch a time: but they are almoſt alwayes heady and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ſeldome are laſting and conſtant in their opinions; they that are to humour them, muſt ſerve many Maſters; who, though they ſeeme, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are, their inferiours; yet grow imperious, upon many occaſions: many actions; of merit, how eminent ſoever, ſhall not prevaile with them to excuſe one miſtake; want of ſucceſſe, though that be all the crime, makes them angry, murmuring and jealous: whereas a Gentleman is better ſpirited, and more reſolute; and though he ſuffereth by it, had rather ſticke to that power that will countenance him, then to that which makes no difference betwixt him and a Peaſant. The Gentleman followes his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution cloſe, and wins of his ſilly neighbours many times, either by his power, by his example, or his diſcourſe, when as they have an eaſie Faith,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112012:9"/>quickely wrought upon, and upon the next turne will fall off in ſholes.</p>
            <p>They are a body certainly of great conſequence, when they are headed and ribbed by the Gentry; but they have a Craven or an unruly courage, (which at beſt may rather be called Obſtinacy then Reſolution) and are far leſſe conſiderable, when the moſt part of the Gentry, or chiefe Citizens di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide themſelves from them.</p>
            <p>We ſhall find the Parliament hath nothing to cement it ſelfe, to increaſe and fix their party, and keep it from ſtaggering, but a little temporary reputation, and a reſolution to hold faſt to the publike good; and this (if things run ſo high as they do now) will be called rebellious ſtubborneſſe, and be branded with the foule imputation of Treaſon. Whereas the King (as the chiefe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Diſpencer of the Common-wealth) is able to fit the humor of every man that he hath a mind to take of: he hath honour for the proud, places of truſt for the ambitious, inferiour offices for the buſie man; favour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and a poſſibility of ſeverall preferments, to invite all ſorts of men to him: He hath the power of a Pardon to hold out like a Lure, to fetch in ſuch as have turned taile; yet, perhaps, would come in againe, but dare not ſtoop till that calls them in.</p>
            <p>The humor of changing is epidemicall; as infectious to the next neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as the Plague; and if it ſhould ſpread forth about <hi>London,</hi> whence ſhall the ſupplies come? A Prince by his Agents will keepe off the aid of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne States from them, but is ſeldome denyed ſome contribution towards his owne defence. And if they contribute any thing, it will be juſt ſo much as ſhall ſerve to hold up the warre; and will give it as fewell to maintaine the fire, not as water to ſuppreſſe and quench it: For they never yeeld aſſiſtance where their advantage ſhall not largely recompence it. And if it ſo fall out, that the intereſt of an adjoyning State ſhall chance to be mingled with the actions of their neighbouring ſubjects, their Prince will uſe all arts (having the moſt expert inſtruments for it) to diſable or take off that party: he may quallifie that State before hand by parting with ſome thing he hath right unto; or may doe it, by corrupting ſome eminent Engineere there; ſome great officers, and ſome of the moſt popular men; or by kindling ſome diviſions amongſt them, ſo to buſie them at home, that whileſt their owne houſe ſeemes to be on fire, and like to burne further, they may not be at leiſure to quench their neighbours flames.</p>
            <p>There is a Preſident that ſeemes to encourage very much the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of this warre; and that is the late ſucceſſe of our brethren in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> But, I feare, if we parallel our preſent condition and theirs together, we ſhall finde, that we ſhall differ point-blancke in moſt circumſtances, but the warre of the cauſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112012:9"/>
            <p n="1">1 When their great worke firſt began, the three Kingdomes were generally diſcontented; and they all did as it were conſpire to its aſſiſtance, either in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret or openly, conceiving it to bee their owne buſineſſe, their owne quarrell.</p>
            <p>Secondly, amongſt our great men here, there were very few ſtood neere the ſterne, and thoſe not at all plauſible with the people. And our chiefe Nobilitie and Gentry had no countenance ſhewed them at Court, and could not on the ſudden be ſo farre engaged on that ſide as the ſervice required, but joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at the Treaty in the North to get eaſie conditions for them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, though the Kings Counſellours had been long practiſing to make their beſt advantage of a Peace, yet they knew not how to beſtirre themſelves properly in a Warre. Very few of them being fit to be Military ſtates-men. Becauſe untill then, Souldiers had never been countenanced; A man in Buffe was a rare ſight in Court.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Papiſts (although their Agents and their Purſes were buſie) never ſhewed themſelves in a body.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Cavalry, both at home, and from abroad, (whence many came to a more uncertaine ſervice,) did beleeve, that they fought for their Country, and not againſt the King, whileſt they oppoſed themſelves againſt his Army.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, they fought againſt another Nation (an old Enemie ſcarce quite reconciled) and had no Reluctancie, no feare of killing a Father, a Brother, a Kinſman (ſcarce a Country-man.) They (being alwayes as politique as cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable) would hardly have accounted us as Brethren, had wee thwarted their Deſignes, we being to be thought ſo farre deere to them, as they may be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited by us.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, The ſeat of the Warre was out of their owne Confines; and they had ſo ordered it, that if their buſineſſe could not be done without the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it: It ſhould be acted in another Countrey, the ſpoyle of which would make no tender conſcience amongſt them to recoile, they being to make their advantage both by inriching themſelves, and weakening us.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, they had not the controling preſence of lawfull Majeſty, which takes off, prevents, and counter-plots the Deſignes of any that are working neere to it.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, (not to looke into more private Reaſons which perhaps might be urged) we ſhall find that the condition and temper of the People and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Scotland,</hi> well weighed with ours (at this time) will be very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and may well divert us from levelling at the ſame ends. And this alſo may be a generall anſwer, they being a People watchfull for their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, had the lucke (with the Diſeaſed in the Goſpell) to ſtep firſt into the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112012:10"/>waters after they were troubled, and found the benefit of it: Whereas thoſe that came after tryed the Cure in vaine.</p>
            <p>But to goe on in our Argument of Advantage or Diſadvantage: When once the people ſhew themſelves to be ſenſible of the ſmart of War, nothing can ſo much wipe away the remembrance of former injuries, and ingratiate any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as to be forwardeſt (though but in meere ſhew) to an Accommodation. The People (not being able to ſee far into the ſecret conſequences of War, and Peace) will begin to looke upon thoſe as their enemies whom they ſhall find moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to Peace. And therefore though a Treaty may bring many weighty In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies to one ſide more then the other; yet the humouring of the people is of ſo much conſequence that it is too great an advantage to let it bee often preſſed and not received with the ſame ſeeming eagerneſſe. Who hath made the beſt uſe of this policie, may be ſeene by the effects of it.</p>
            <p>The King is the more likely to draw to him the affections of the people, in that the preſſures and miſcarriages of his late Government are paſſed, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expiated by his acknowledgement of them, and a promiſe of redreſſe, and are as it were forgotten by them, who reſent more their preſent Grievances (not conſidering the difference and the quality of them) then a thouſand over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed tranſgreſſions, which are driven out of their Remembrances by aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting every miſtake, every circumſtance of injury and violence, which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, either againſt their wil or upon neceſſity (the common excuſe of States-men) doth commit.</p>
            <p>The King (a Syllable, of as much advantage as another Army) in his very Name is ſacred and powerfull, and ſhakes the conſciences of many, who would elſe have willing hands, and ready Purſes to oppoſe his Army. Hee hath the advantage of the written Law, which hee can uſe now, in his defence; and by the Authority of it, joyned with the Power of his Sword, can thunder out Accuſations, and perhaps the Penalties of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt thoſe whom he ſhall call his oppoſers. Hee hath a Counſell ſo well mingled, that he hath ſome verſed and cunning in the Law, and that know how to turne it to the moſt neceſſary uſe: Some crafty in all the windings of State; ſome experienced in all the Deſignes of Warre. His Intelligencers are in the very Boſome of his Antagoniſts, or elſe his Agents conjure: and his owne counſells are ſecrets, till hee thinkes fit to divulge them. The Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of his Army are many and expert, and are not clamorous for pay, as if they ſerved him to make him great, rather then themſelves immediatly rich, and ſeeme to be fixed in their Faith to his ſervice: The Nobility and Gentry about Hirn, beare their owne charges, and aſſiſt his: His Army is big enough to defend it ſelfe untill the Spring, the time of Action appeares: and what it is likely to be by that time, let every man judge that conſiders His partie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112012:10"/>and almoſt in all Counties. And it is a fond thing certainly to thinke his Army can want Ammunition, having any Port open: or that it will want Money more then the other; If the Kingdome hath it, the Souldier will not be without it: if it have not, they muſt feed on free-coſt.</p>
            <p>Thus wee find by theſe many Circumſtances, that the Parliament hath a conſiderable oppoſite. It will now be in vaine to ſumme up all the ſtrength and advantages which ſurely are very many, that the Parliament hath got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for its defence, and to goe through with its Deſignes; We heare ſo much of them every day, of their power, of their ſucceſſe, that I ſhall not need to enlarge them. My endeavour is not to magnifie the Powers of one above tho other, but to ſhew how conſiderble they both are to undoe one another, and the whole State. Our Bells and Pamphlets have told us of Victories that have been given at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> at <hi>Chichester,</hi> in <hi>York</hi>-ſhire, and all this while I cannot ſee any reaſon to rejoyce, or to hope the buſineſſe is any whit neerer an end: for by all this it only appeares, that they are able to maintaine the Warre, not finiſh it. Theſe petty conqueſts doe not ſo much improve the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Parliament; as the certaine noiſe of the thriving forces in the Weſt, and that yet dangerous Army now in the North, doth ſhake them. Which may be feared (as things are now every where) may grow able to maſter thoſe parts of the Kingdome, and we know not how ſoone may bee ready for any other ſervice that emergent occaſions ſhall require.</p>
            <p>The Reſult then of all that hath been ſaid, is but this, We have ſeene that our Peace hath beene abuſed, that the abuſe of it hath begot a Warre; That the Warre hath already brought in many Miſeries, that thoſe miſeries are ready to encreaſe, even to our Ruine: And that this Ruine will be certaine, if a ſudden Peace interrupt it not. Thus we now ſeeme to have before us a Fatall choyce, Peace or Ruine. It is time then that we looke about us: and although wee heare theſe ſtruglings to be called Sedition and Rebellion on the one ſide, and Malignancy and Treaſon on the other, yet I hope it will be none of theſe, for the ſubject to looke after, and ſecure his endangered Being. It will ſurely bee ſomewhat excuſable, if we deale a little familiarly with both ſides, whileſt we judge of our conditions according to the light we have, from the Reſults of their Actions, and their many Declarations, which we have reaſon to looke upon as ſo many appeales to the people, who (as matters now ſtand) are like to be the Judges, the executioners, and ſufferers in this Bloody Tryall.</p>
            <p>And whileſt we are to conſider our owne Intereſts, let us lay aſide partiality, and thoſe paſſions and conceits which will not give us leave to ſeeke Peace the neereſt and the beſt way: Let us owne Reaſon, on which ſide ſoever we ſhall find it. It is worth a mans wonder to ſee on both ſides men that have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112012:11"/>reckoned (and deſervedly) amongſt the moſt wiſe and ſober; to ſee theſe bent to ſuch extreames, that they will juſtifie their Party in every circumſtance and ſo fix their opinions to one ſide, as if infallibilitie were inherent to it, and, as if they were not at all concerned in the Actions of the other party. I ſhall for my owne part rejoyce, that I am not ſo wiſe as theſe men, and ſhall be glad if I ſhall be of their Forme, that have indifferent wits, and middle judgements. And ſhall argue (as I have hitherto done) if Reaſon offer it ſelfe on both ſides, unleſſe ſome mighty Polititian ſhall be able to perſwade me that this State may ſubſiſt in its wonted Glory and Eminency without a King, or in its happy temper of Freedome and Subjection without a Parliament. When either of theſe Paradoxes ſhall be proved. I ſhall ſilently heare extreames maintained without a reply. But I looke preſently to be cryed down as guilty of that hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crime, which this exorbitant Age calls Moderation. Yet ere I be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, let us goe to Iſſue, and we ſhall find upon the Tryall, how juſtifiable my how neceſſary this kind of Tranſgreſſion (if it muſt be ſo ſtiled) now is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true Character of a Moderate man I conceive to be this; He is one that loves his Countrey ſo well, that he grieves to ſee it deſtroyed out of a ſaving policy, one that is not a friend to this War, not becauſe he is afraid to dy, but becauſe he would here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after live in an even and well poyzed Temper. One, that could never be ſo well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied of the neceſſity why this War began, as he is now, why it ſhould ſee an end; which though he longs for yet knowes not how to pray for a Victory. One that in earnest loves the King, and thinks him Eſſentiall to the Being of a Parliament, and the life of this, to the well-being of all hereafter. One that honours, not adores the Parliament becauſe he ſees they alſo are but men: &amp; rather wiſhes them ſafe, and what they ſhould be, then Omnipotent. One that would have his Religion nor gawdy nor ſtripped ſtark-naked. One that loves both Law and Goſpell, and would gladly have thoſe that meddle with either, to hold themſelves cloſer to their Text. One that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually aſmuch afraid of the medling ſevere Clergy of</hi> New-England, <hi>as of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious pragmatick Clergy of old</hi> England. <hi>One that is ſorry to ſee it more ſeaſonable then ſafe, to ſpeake truth. One that would have Peace not as an effect of War, but of an Accommodation. To conclude he is one that is yet an admirer of Peace, and is earneſt to ſee a farther Tryall who avoids it moſt &amp; ſo hinders him of it: you ſhall then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have him leave his Center, and betake himſelfe to one ſide, as if by that he had found out his enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We might take this man in pieces and examine in how many circumſtances, he can (is yet) be hurtfull to the State, but we will not tye our ſelves to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, yet we ſhall find all or moſt of theſe Notions to be requiſite in every one that will conſider and follow his Intereſt as he is an Engliſh ſubject.</p>
            <p>Our contention in generall ſeems to be like theirs that have gone to Law for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112012:11"/>ſome Royalties, ſome Priviledges in a Mannor, and have conſumed all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes to maintain the ſuit, &amp; at laſt after great expence, &amp; with much ado, have perhaps left to their poſterity an enlarged title, but an empty eſtate.</p>
            <p>We can laugh at ſuch folly as this in others, and yet will not ſee it in our ſelves. It will ere long be our owne caſe, if we will not come to compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If wee could have thought it ſafe to have cloſed, when the King ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to open his Armes, by his offer the twentieth of <hi>January,</hi> 1641. (or ſince when Hee invited to a Treaty by his Meſſage from <hi>Nottingham</hi>) or to have gone ſo far in a Conference, as to have knowne what was really the Difference on both ſides: It is very likely our Diviſions now had beene leſſe and fewer: and though perhaps ſome ſcars would have yet been left unworne away, which muſt be the Worke of Time; yet our gaping wounds, the wide breaches which now make us Miſerable, had certainly been better cloſed, then we can ever hope to ſee them hereafter. Heaven hath given us leave to ſee another <hi>Ianuary,</hi> another offer to a Reconciliation: Let us conſider how many Miſchiefs have thruſt themſelves upon us ſince the laſt yeare; and how many worſe then thoſe, will crowde in, if another year muſt go round in ſuch Diſtractions.</p>
            <p>To the earneſt proſecutors of this War, that had rather looſe themſelves then their expectations, this may be ſaid. When the General marched out of <hi>London,</hi> there was ſome Reaſon to hope that he might be able to performe thoſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which the Parliament furniſhed him with. And although if ſucceſſe had gone along with the Deſigne, if ſome skirmiſhes, or a battaile might have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his employment, it might perhaps have turned to the quiet and advantage of the eſtate; yet ſeeing that without infinite and dangerous difficulties, that which was aimed at cannot be reached by the ſword; it is good reaſon that it ſhould be ſheathed; and this Rule is ſomtimes worth-holding unto; ſeeing wee cannot have what we would, let us have what we may: for perhaps even that which might now be obtained, may be denied us at the next parley. For ſome are perſwaded, that more favourable conditions might once have bin agreed on then can now be gained.</p>
            <p>But let me not be miſtaken: I cannot find yet any conſiderable number of men to be ſo far in love with peace, as to entertain it on any conditions. For moſt men know, that ſuch a Peace may cut our Throats; or if it be ſoft, and want an edge to undoe us ſo quickly as the Sword: yet it may ſtifle all our Liberties; we may be murthered with a Feather-bed, and ſmothered with Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Nor would I believe, that ſuch an over-reaching Peace as this, is urged upon us. The ſubject is told that nothing is pretended to, which may make for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112012:12"/>his good; but it ſhall be granted. And I am drawn to hope the beſt, for theſe following Motives.</p>
            <p>No Prince ever gave ſuch ingagements to his People of a ſucceeding happy Government, as he hath done by his ſeverall Remonſtrances: And if experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had delivered half that to us, which Eloquence would now perſwade us to believe: Hee were envious to himſelf that would not make Bon-fires for every Declaration: yet ſome, (and wiſe men to) adviſe us, that whilſt we are ſhewed theſe fetters of Gold, wee ſhould not ſo admire the gliſtering of them, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be bound by them: but though we may thank them for their advice, yet it is hoped we ſhall not need it: For, beſides the many Vowes regiſtred with Heaven and Earth, we have other aſſurances offered to us: the firſt, are onely to inform and win our Reaſon, or our Affection, not to lead our faith; which ſhall be more really convinced, (as 'tis good reaſon it ſhould) when he ſhall agree to ſuch propoſitions, as all reaſonable men ſhall be ſatisfied with. This (if I miſtake not) we are promiſed. And beſides; I would not be ſuch an utter oppoſite to the Cavaliers, (I mean to the moſt diſengaged Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Kings party;) as to believe that they can be ſo far tranſported with vanity, as to ſell all the reſt of the Kingdom into ſlavery; to purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſome ſtrange immunities: ſeeing their children if not themſelves muſt be ſlaves, as well as the iſſue of the <hi>Round-heads;</hi> ſurely theſe will joyne (laying aſide all Malice &amp; Paſſion) becauſe Poſterity is concerned in it, to get ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions for this Parliament; and eaſie conditions for the Subject in generall. This I hopefor, although wee have ſeen in many the metamorphoſing power of a little private intereſt. But if it ſo unhappily fall out, that any very high things be propoſed, and ſtood upon, on the one ſide, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a little with neceſſity (which our Stateſmen have hitherto been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to make their Miſtris, and have obeyed very far) or that reaſonable and neceſſary things, ſhall not be granted on the otherſide; ſo that, that peace, which is prayed for by ſo many, muſt be ſtill held from us: how wretched a condition will this State at the beſt be reduced to? For though his Majeſty make us gracious Promiſes, and hath perhaps contrived in his juſt Thoughts, an equall and eaſie Government, yet if this War continue it's Revels, Hee may not be left in a capacity to make us ſo happy, as hee would doe: For the moſt conſtant men, muſt be contented to change their Reſolutions with the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations of time. And, what unexpected effects attend on War? Suppoſe the lengthening of this War, ſo ſhake the Eſtates of the Nobility, and Gentry about the King, as that there will be little left to mayntain them like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when the War is ended: Who do we think is, as it were, bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire their fortunes? And whether will not they (reduced to ſuch Neceſſities)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112012:12"/>be contented to enlarge that Power; that may be ſo enabled to Revenge, and requite them, making the Publick Intereſt, to bend a little to theirs? And that amongſt theſe, there will not be ſome Chiefs, ſome that unſeen; and cloſely will winde up Prerogative, to make themſelves greater? And doe we believe that the Nature and Diſpoſition of the People will not be altered; who being tired and almoſt, worn out with the Contentions of the King and Parliament, will more eaſily undergo ſuch things, as they would heretofore have called Slavery. And although the Prince have no ayme at it, yet before hee ſhall be aware, he ſhall find himſelfe engaged, (by the Concurrencies of ſo many Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that conduce to it,) in a higher and more abſolute Government: ſo that the Conſtitution of this State, will become a little unlike it ſelfe: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, wee muſt know that Princes, and all ſuch as have the Government of a Common-wealth, are compelled ſometimes by a kind of Neceſſity; to diſence wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>he ſetled Rules of Law, for Reaſon of State; and it cannot be expected th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a Prince, if hee be wiſe, as well as Pious; ſhall be ſo ſuperſtitious to the ſtrict ſence of any Proteſtations, as to neglect his Intereſt, and the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his State; which may (as it may happen) ſuffer very much whileſt he makes a conſcience to doe things fit and requiſite: And there will not then want Men of both Cownes that will prove, that conveniency and neceſſity ſhall excuſe the conſcience in ſuch a caſe. Would we avoid theſe inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Let us not then run the hazard of them. Let us prevent a delayed Victory by a ſudden Agreement.</p>
            <p>But, I ſeeme to gueſſe too confidently of the Succeſſe ſo far off; for there is another conſiderable Army in the Field; and after infinite bloudſhed, it is poſſible enough that this may bee Victorious. What muſt wee then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect?</p>
            <p>It is likely the nineteen Propoſitions wil be very reaſonable things then: It will ſeeme requiſite then, that Monarchy, or that which is called Prerogative, ſhould be circumſcribed within more popular Limits. That ſome Wiſer, ſome Honeſter, ſome more Pious Men, ſome that are Unbyaſed with private reſpects or opinions; ſome that have hazarded themſelves (and more) for the common good, ſhould be Superviſors of the State; and ſettle it in ſuch an order as ſhould better pleaſe and benefit the People (ſuch rare men as theſe are, the State hath had need of; I pray God a competent number of them may be found, if ſuch an ocaſion ſhould call for them.) And who knows, whether they will be able to ſtay here? For, it may perhaps ſo fall out, that ſome other Politick ſecurity (not to be gueſſed at) may ſeem neceſſary to be innovated; (which this State hath wanted: yet perhaps not needed for many hundred years.) And Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions come not alone: Rules of Government are like links in a Chaine; they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112012:13"/>hang one by another, and require proportion, and Evenneſſe; if a new one be added; it muſt be warily fitted to the reſt; or the reſt reduced as neer as can be to the Reſemblance of the other. And what doe we believe will ſatisfie the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Victors, the People? Will not their ends and deſires be as various, as their humours are now? Will they ſubmit in their Opinions to that, which the Judgments of thoſe in the Parliament (as many as the War and the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it, will leave) ſhall agree upon? Or, will it lye in the Power of the Parliament, when the State ſhall be in ſo generall a confuſion, as an expiring War muſt leave it in, to order the government ſo, that the King may Rule; and the People obey, as beſeems them? I would fain aſſure my ſelf that they might be able to performe all the good that they intend and promiſe; but, ſome thing like Reaſon, will not give me leave. I have conſidered, that thoſe that undertake to ſtand at the Stern, though their wils, and their Ends direct them a ſtraight courſe; yet they muſt bee contented to ſteere according to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Winde, and Temper which they ſhall finde the Seas in.</p>
            <p>Good God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will it not then be madneſſe to fight on, if ſuch as theſe are like to be the Effects of Victory? But Victory is ſuch a word, as I know not how to uſe it in ſuch a Diſcourſe; for there can be truly no ſuch thing in this Action: Loſſe will be all the gaine wee can expect from it: and we find that the prevailing Sword muſt weare ſuch a Power, as can ſcarce be proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the State: and our next Government muſt have a Tincture at the leaſt of the humours of thoſe that ſhall become Maſters of the Field; which may perhaps be of our owne Nation, or of another, ſo uncertaine are the iſſues of War, It being an obſervation that the diffention of any people hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways bin an invitation to their Neighbours. If this Warre be defenſive on the Kings part, and if his Councell hath no other Deſigne in the holding it up, then meerly his Safety, and ſo much honour as may reach to the good of the People; and ſo far only the Affaires of the King: Wee have good reaſon to believe that a Peace would be welcome to him: And to hope that as he is reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to Divinity, ſo he will reflect upon his Mercy as well as his Juſtice: and believe that hee may be as much honoured in forgetting the injuries of any; as he can be in the Revenge of them; eſpecially, ſeeing hee ſhews his Grace to his Subjects, whoſe Ruine would indeed be his weakning; though I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this be none of <hi>Machiavils</hi> Principles. I would ſay more, but that I would not be ſo bold, as to give Inſtructions to a King: yet the affixing this line here in the middle, to look both wayes, can ſurely doe no harme.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112012:13"/>
            <q>
               <hi>Arma Tenenti, omnia dat, Qui Juſta negat.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Nor ſhall I undertake to be wiſer then my Teachers, and give Rules to the Parliament. I ſhall onely adviſe them to remember what they are; of whom they are made; and why they are met. And becauſe they want the winde (the Auſpicious Gale of Complying Majeſty) and enough of the Tyde (the full ſtreame of the Peoples affections,) and ſeeing the ſtorm grows high; and it is fowl weather, it may be better to hale-in, and betake themſelves to a Harbour, leſt the State ſuffer Shipwrack, whileſt the Helm ſeems to be in their hands.</p>
            <p>But I may be a little bolder with my Fellow Subjects, and ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what truely is their Intereſt now, whileſt their ſafety is thus farre endangered.</p>
            <p>Slavery (the fear of which is accounted worſe then death, by ſuch as have been born Free-men) could never befall us, if we did not help to binde our ſelves by our own hands, and admit it by our own Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; The People while they hold together, are like a caſt Ocean; an abſolute Power cannot poſſibly wade through to it's ends, unleſſe they fall back one from another, and become like thoſe wonderfull Walls of Water, which gave the Iſraelites leave to paſſe through on dry Land: Should then fond Engliſh thus farre ſevere themſelves, we ſhould alſo be a wonder to Poſterity. This is feared on both ſides, and avoided rightly by neither. We fight to make one ſide Great; which being done, the other muſt needs be too little: If the inferiour parts of the Body, the Members of it, be made to ſwell beyond their due proportion, we preſently diſlike the Symptomes, and fear a Dropſie; And that body whoſe head is ſwelled, and made greater by ill humours, then it ſhould be, is of a diſeaſed Conſtitution, hath but weak Limbes; and almoſt nothing but leanneſſe every where elſe.</p>
            <p>There may be Reaſon to be as well affraid of an extravagant popular Power, as the exorbitancies of Monarchy. But, whileſt we endeavour to avoid the one, Let us be carefull that we do not engage our ſelves in the other: It were well therefore, That when Propoſitions ſhall be tendred to His Majeſty, That the Nobility and Gentry, (for I hope the former Delinquents, and Papiſts do not adviſe, though they aſſiſt) which have ſeparated themſelves from the Parliament, ſhould diſcover themſelves without Paſſion, according to their true Intereſts, how farre they would have it ſtoop in their Requeſts: Let them conſider how great, or how little they would have had the Power of Prerogative to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112012:14"/>have been, when they groaned under the large Extent of it, and when they had nothing in their Eye, but the meer good, and ſafety of the Common-wealth, which is now in the ſame, yet in more danger, then ever they ſaw it. How farre they would then have had, the abuſers of their Princes Power; The deſtroyers of Law and Juſtice; The cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats of the State (the Monopolizers;) How farre I ſay, they would then have had theſe puniſhed, and made Examples; How much of the inſulting Clergies wings, they would then have been glad to have clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Let their zeal for a Reformation both in Church, and State, be ſuch, in every circumſtance, as it was then; and more need not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fired. Let them not, Becauſe they are angry with themſelves, (I mean with their Fellow Subjects,) Revenge themſelves upon Poſterity, by ſetting up againſt themſelves, not only a larger Power, but an Authority alſo, even by their own Grants, by their own Swords. It lyes not in the Power of the Subject to conferre more toward their ſlavery, then to pull down a Parliament (upon what neceſſity or pretence ſoever) with their own hands: This ſhall be a laſting Preſident, and Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all Ages; and a warrant to all Princes to diſcountenance them, ſince they work not better effects upon the State; and that ſide muſt be ſure to own all the guilt, which ſhall be overthrown. A Parliament will be ſaid to be the ſole Author of theſe Miſeries; Thus, It will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the diſdain, which was alwayes hitherto the Darling of the People. Thus a perpetuall Prejudice ſhall ſtick upon all hereafter; and then what uſe ſhall the overborne Subject have of his Sanctuary? If it want Reverence, it will want Power; If it want Power, it will onely ſerve to give away our Eſtates, not amend them. And is it not likely when the Improvident People ſhall inflame their Prince in a Conteſtation, where themſelves are ſo neerly concerned, That it will inſtruct ſuch a one, as ſhall by Himſelf, or His Councellours hereafter, have an aym at an abſolute command; to ſtruggle with them, at any time, when they aske in Parliament for things covenient, or neceſſary; and to call it a Beam of His Prerogative, though it be indeed but a falſe Reflection of an Uſurped Light? Let them ſeriouſly conſider, to which ſide they ought in right Reaſon to give the moſt advantage, in theſe Propoſitions. When a Prince wins any thing from His People (much more when they urge it upon Him) He will be ſure to hold faſt what He hath, and many times Improves, never diminiſhes it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if the Subject gain any extraordinary thing from the Crown, (how
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112012:14"/>neceſſary ſoever) with what difficulty is it enjoyed? How many Tricks and Invaſions have the Inſtruments of State to cozen the People of the benefit of it?</p>
            <p>Our Predeceſſors have been as much afraid of the greatneſſe of their Soveraign, though over other Nations, as of the Diminution of their own Eſtate; and therefore did their beſt to diminiſh His Power, or Fortunes, leſt by enlarging Himſelf upon a Neighbouring Adverſary, He might forget Himſelf, and become too high for them. Surely then, ſome ſuch care is due to the Affairs at this time; yet it muſt be averred. That he that robs his Prince of His honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, impaires the reputation of his Countrey; and he that would fix any honour in Him, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be communicable to the Common-wealth, ſins againſt both.</p>
            <p>The Punctuallity and Nicity of the Honour and Greatneſſe of the King, hath ſeldome been enough to hold up a Warre, with wary Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, eſpecially among themſelves; Let them take care to do things ſafe and honourable for the Common-wealth (of which He is chief,) and it will be impoſſible, That the Kings Honour, and ſafety, ſhould not be mingled with it. I hope He will finde as much Honour in ſaving a periſhing Kingdom, as if He were gaining a new one. And whileſt He thus makes a Conqueſt on His Peoples hearts. He renders Himſelf greater, then His driving Councellors could make Him, were they at the end of their Deſignes. It were worth our joy to ſee Him return triumphing, with, but not over His People.</p>
            <p>And as that Party ſhould do their duty; ſo is there Reaſon, That they on the other ſide ſhould do theirs. Let them remember that they have a King; That whileſt He is in a Cloude, we are in the ſhade, and want that Influence which may revive the State, and make it flouriſh. Let no man ſo dote upon a Parliament, as to think it wants errours; nor conceit there can be any Government contrived ſo proper to the Nature and Conſtitution of this State, as Monarchy, ſo circumſcribed, and quallified as ours is, by the Wiſedom and care of our Predeceſſors, the providence of this Parliament. Let them lay aſide violent conceits, and expectations; and let them believe, (having ſo good Reaſons for it) That they will ſooner reach, their Deſtruction, then that thorough-Reformation, which by many is aymed at.<note place="margin">The Speech of the Chan: to <hi>Hen.</hi> 5.</note> Let every man value the bleſſings of Union, by the Miſeries we have undergone by Diviſion; Let us ſeek Peace earneſtly, but let it not, as yet, be by this Argument; <hi>Bellum faciamus, ut Pacem habeamus, nam finis Belli Pax eſt:</hi> but, here
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112012:15"/>it will prove too true, That <hi>Finis hujus Belli Ruina erit.</hi> Yet, let us know, That Peace (leſt we be over-reached in the match) muſt now be woed with circumſpection: That the Managers of Treaties, are State Jugglers; and that the moſt Intereſſed men are likelieſt to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in it: That thoſe therefore that never had any minde to the Warre, have Reaſon to be carefull how the Peace be concluded: That it is requiſite, both ſides ſhould make themſelves as conſiderable as they can at ſuch a time: That to pay the Army now, is to improve the benefit of a Peace; which, at beſt, by this kinde of concluſion will yeild leſſe advantage to the Subject, then to the King; though it be now abſolutely neceſſary for both.</p>
            <p>And we have Reaſon to make the beſt uſe of this nick of Time, and not deferre it an inſtant farther.</p>
            <p>For after all this endeavour of both ſides: after every one hath done his beſt, toward the great cure of this languiſhing State; the diſeaſe hath been let runne ſo farre, That it will almoſt be beyond all hope, that we ſhall ever ſee a recovery: Into ſo deſperate a Conſumption are we fallen, partly by their fault, that ſhould have had more care of our health; in whoſe Power we all thought it once lay, to prepare ſuch Preſervatives for us, that we might have been ſetled in ſuch a healthfull Conſtitution, that none of theſe evills could now have vexed us. Our ſad Caſe is now ſuch, That we have an Incenſed God; an angry King; a threatning Councell; a heady Clergy; a divided Nobility; a diſcontented Gentry; a diſtempered People; a diſtracted Religion; an unhinged State; a confuſed Government; undermining Adverſaries; a Civill Warre; an increaſe of Souldiers; conſumption of Treaſure; diſ-union in united Kingdoms; loſt Reputation; an unniverſall Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie; a defection from the Principles of ſound Policy; a Parliament which ſhould be the Redreſſe of all theſe, made quite otherwiſe, to us, by ſome that have abuſed it: and generally ſuch a conſpiracy; ſuch a complying of ill Symptomes; that even Miracles muſt be wrought, or elſe we periſh. In a word, Such is our doubtfull condition; That even a Peace, may deſtroy us; But a Warre, muſt. We had not need then, neglect any opportunities of being happy, ſeeing we are ſo beſet with miſery. And we ſhall finde now, That both ſides are ſomewhat evenly ballanced: And it concerns the Subject on both ſides, (eſpecially one fide) to keep them ſo, untill the Parley ſhall be concluded; which if it ſhall now take no effect, may juſtly make us deſpair of ſuch an other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112012:15"/>Hint to a Reconcilement; For we ſhall ſcarce ever again ſee them ſo well poyſed, ſo fit for a compoſure; ſeeing now their equall Powers may make them afraid of each other. It may be now hoped (if ever) (ſo that both ſides will do their parts, according to their Intereſts;) That Truth, and Peace may conclude the Treaty. I do not mean ſuch a Truth, as the Rigid Antagoniſts of both ſides, intend.</p>
            <p>Nor am Lable to give you the Character of this Truth; ſince it is yet to be agreed on: Yet I thus conceive of it. It is a <hi>Medium</hi> betwixt the two Extreams, which both ſides ſeem to aym at, whileſt they are at this diſtance: by which (if we are not decreed to confuſion) Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be ſo ſetled, That our Clergy may no more be States-men, and better Church-men; That our Laiety may not intermeddle with Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks; That our Formalities and Ceremonies in Religion, may not drown the ſubſtance of it; and that we may not quite looſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to make ſure not to be any more troubled with the ſhaddow; That to Preach often may not be counted an offence; and that to apply themſelves to ſchiſme and ſedition, may not be called Preaching: that the reſolved Proteſtant may not ſee his Religion ſo altered, ſo meanly dreſſed, as not to be like it ſelf; Nor the weaker Proteſtant, ſee it ſo Gay, ſo full of Trym, that his humble Conſcience dares ſcarce own it: Thus we may provide, On the one hand againſt the encreaſe of Papiſts, And on the other for the regaining of Separatiſts.</p>
            <p>And for that other Truth, which we would have in the State: I think we can make a neerer approach to it, by no other way, then an Accommodation. State-Truth is the Brat of Imagination, and never had any reall being: no Government was ever ſo refined, by an innovating Reformation, but it had defects, or extravagancies; and by the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of the ſucceeding States-men, quickly ſetled into as much (though not the ſame) corruption: when Ambition, and Intereſt ſhall be weeded out of the hearts of men, I will look for this Purity, this Truth. But we have heard long ſince. That <hi>Terras Aſtraea reliquit,</hi> Therefore I ſhall hope only to finde it in Heaven: In the mean time, we ſhall in vain look for Purity, in that which we call Truth, if it muſt be dyed in more of our Bloud. I had rather ſee a little, contributed to the Weal of the State, by the hands of both; then a great deal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated by a ſingle Power: the one I ſhall hope to enjoy with Peace; the other will never be kept without ſtrong contention.</p>
            <p>But if both ſides will obſtinately keep their diſtance: If the one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112012:16"/>cryes out for Peace with Honour; the other for Peace with Truth; and ſcorn to entertain Peace, unleſſe they may have ſo much of both as they demand: Surely, this unhappy Nation, betwixt theſe their great Champions is like to looſe it's Peace, Truth, and Honour.</p>
            <p>I will now Ramble no further into their contemplations; I was big of theſe Thoughts, and could not be quiet untill I was delivered of them, though in my private Papers. Thus, many times doth a minde fill'd with grief, finde eaſe by emptying it ſelf in Complaints, though it can meet with no other Redreſſe.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe, being grounded upon our immediate condition (if things muſt runne on in their old Carere,) may in many things, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be out of date, ere a few dayes paſſe, and be like an Almanack, calculated for the laſt year; and it is very poſſible, (and yet not out of Levity) that ere long, I may alſo vary from ſome things, that ſeem now to be my opinion: For, where Reaſon diſcovers it ſelf, I am reſolved to go along with her. And there may be many Reſpects, to make an unintereſſed man, to change his opinions; and the party, to which he ſeemed neereſt in his Affections. The diſcreet, or politique carriage of a buſineſſe, may make it worſe, or better.</p>
            <p>That cauſe which was the moſt dangerous at the firſt, and had the leaſt merit in it, may through the extremities of the contrary Party, be ſafeſt, and moſt deſerving at the laſt. And though an Even, and Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Man be unwilling to engage himſelf in Warre, on either ſide; yet, if it ſhall appear by the Perverſneſſe of any, That no hope, No poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Peace be left him, but by the Sword: It will then be held the beſt Piety to be a Souldier. <hi>Nam Pia Arma, quibus nulla, niſi in Armis, Spes eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Difficile eſt Satyras non ſcribere.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112012:16"/>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:112012:17"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:112012:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
